

Conor M. Finlay

SENIOR RESEARCH FELLOW

Trinity Translational Medicines Insitute, Trinity College Dublin

□+353 857148825 | **☑** cofinlay@tcd.ie; conor.finlay@manchester.ac.uk | **⊡** 0000-0001-8285-0903 | **⊡** conorisco

I **y** conorisco

Cellular immunologist with bioinformatics skills

Research interests_

I am a cellular Immunologist with three core skills: *in vivo* models of inflammation, bioinformatics and clinical research. My current research obsession is regulation of mononuclear phagocyte (macrophage/denrtiic cells) differentiation during inflammation on a single cell level.

Roles_

SENIOR RESEARCH FELLOW, TRINITY COLLEGE DUBLIN

- COVID19 Strategic partnership
- TCD Single cell Core development
- Trinity Kidney Health Centre, Prof. Mark A Little.

HONORARY RESEARCH FELLOW, UNIVERSITY OF MANCHESTER

- Co-managing Medical Research Council programme grant with Prof Allen
- · Bioinformatics collaborations
- · Core facility engagement

Past Employment_

Research Fellow Trinity College Dublin

SUPERVISOR: PROF MARK LITTLE

2021

Hired to lead single cell RNA-sequencing aspect of the Science foundation Ireland COVID strategic partnership.

Research Associate University of Manchester

SUPERVISOR: PROF JUDITH ALLEN.

2017-2021

 Origin, heterogeneity, proliferation and effector function of macrophages during helminth infection and type 2 immune responses. Funding: Medical Research Council/Wellcome Trust

Lecturer (teaching relief)

Trinity College Dublin

SCHOOL OF BIOCHEMISTRY AND IMMUNOLOGY

2016-2017

• I took on the teaching duties for a senior professor for 1 year including undergraduate practicle supervision, undergraduate and masters level teaching, examinations and corrections.

Post-doctoral Researcher Trinity College Dublin

SUPERVISOR: PROF KINGSTON HG MILLS.

2013-2016

• Research projects: 1. IP-protected translational project identifying and testing novel helminth-derived proteins as potential therapeutics for inflammatory disease. 2. Role of mast cells in the alternative activation of macrophages via IL-33. 3. Circadian regulation of autoimmune disease

Pharmaceutical advertisement and event reviewer

Bristol-Myers Squibb

Paid internship

2007

 Reviewed 5 years of pharmaceutical adversitments for assessment of complience. Created and managed database for reporting issues and producing analysis documents. Liasing with marketing and scientific teams to address and solve issues.

NOVEMBER 2021 CONOR M. FINLAY · CURRICULUM VITAE



Informatics Training Scheme (Wellcome Trust TPA)

PROGRAMMING AND COMPUTATIONAL APPROACHES TO BIOLOGY MODULES

PhD in Immunology

IMMUNE MODULATION BY THE HELMINTH PARASITE FASCIOLA HEPATICA

• Supervisor: Kingston Mills

BA(Mod) in Natural Sciences

BIOCHEMISTY AND IMMUNOLOGY GRADE: 1:1

University of Manchester

2020

Trinity College Dublin

ige Dubii

Trinity College Dublin

2007

SKILLS

Animal models of Disease: Experimental autoimmune encephalomyelitis, Litomosoides sigmodontis infection, OVA/Alum and dust mite-induced airway hypersensitivity, dextran sodium sulphate-induced colitis, circadian rhythm modulation, B16 melanoma, Sterile peritonitis, IL-4-complex administration, House airway hypersensitivity, Fasciola hepatica infection, Bordetella pertussis infection.

Laboratory techniques: In vitro cell culture, FACS & MACS cell sorting, flow cytometry, mass cytometry, tissue digestion, ELISA, enzyme assays, RT-qPCR, confocal microscopy, Amnis Image Stream, sample preparation for mass spectrometry and single cell RNA-sequencing. Basic experience with PCR, genotyping, immunoblots and library preparation for Next Generation Sequencing.

Clinical research: Preparation of cells from human blood. Biobanking, clinical database management. Patient stratification and statistical analysis. Working in as part of a multi-disciplinary scientific-clinical research team. Data curation and integration.

Programming, Data analysis, Statistics & Visualisation: R (Fluent), Phyton (Intermediate), Unix/Bash (Beginner). Data analysis/visualisation in and in R using Tidyverse and ggplot2. Advanced user of Microsoft Office applications, TreeStar FlowJo and GraphPad Prism. Competent user of Adobe Illustrator and pathway analysis tools e.g. IPA. Strong background in statistics and its application to experimental design and interpretation of results. Database creation and maintenance. Creation of Shiny Apps. Basic knowledge of computer science and use of high-performance computer clusters.

Bioinformatics. Analysis of microarray/bulk RNA-seq datasets analysis using the DESeq2 and EdgeR packages. Single cell analysis using Scater within SingleCellExperiment, pySCENIC, Velocyto, Seurat, FlowCore, FlowSOM, CytofKit. Dimensionality reduction: PCA, t-SNE and UMAP. Progression analysis using monocle3, Destiny and RNA velocity. Clustering using Phonograph, DevSM, FlowSOM hclust and treeclust.

Grants

MR/V011235/1 Programme Grant

Medical Research Council

2.26 MILLION GBP CO-INVESTIGATOR

2021

• "Macrophages in type 2 immunity: unravelling susceptibility and resistance to tissue nematode infection". Funded, 2.26 million GBP. Co-wrote grant and provided scientific design and preliminary data. I was awarded an honorary research fellow position at UoM to facilitate ongoing involvement in this project when I left Manchester to return to Ireland.

Building Engagements in Health Research Scheme

Internal TCD

10K EUR. CO-APPLICANT

2021

- Co-Applicant as scientific lead with Jennifer Scott (TCD, ICAT fellow) as medical lead. 'Nanoparticle modulation of neutrophil and monocyte responses to ANCA'
 - Shortlisted for UKRI Innovation/Rutherford Fund Skills Development Fellowship (Computational Biology), Sep 2017.

Presentations

ORAL

2021	Cytokine and interferon society meeting	Cardiff
2019	Irish Society of Immunology	RCSI, Dublin
2019	BSI Type 2 Immunology Meeting	Manchester
2019	KU Leuven, UZ Gasthuisberg Campus	KU Leuven
2015	Molecular and cellular biology of helminth parasites IX	Hydra, Greece
2015	TBSI Post-Doc Research Day	TCD, Dublin
2015	1st TBSI-Weimann joint Immunology conference	Rehovot, Israel
2015	European Congress of Immunology	Vienna
2009	European Congress of Immunology	Berlin

POSTER

2019	British Society of Immunology	Liverpool
2018	Type 2 Immunity in Homeostasis and Disease	Bruges
2017	British Society of Immunology	Brighton
2016	British Society of Immunology	Liverpool
2015	Frontiers in neurology	TCD, Dublin
2014	Cytokine and interferon society meeting	Melbourne
2012	Keystone: Biology of Cytokines	Colorado
2011	Cytokine and interferon society meeting	Florence

Outreach and organisation

- **Discover Research Night**, Dublin Sep 2014. Marie Skłodowska-Curie-funded. I was the event organiser responsible for public engagement at Trinity Biomedical Sciences Institute, 8 weeks' full-time.
- **10th International Symposium on Bordetella**, Sep 2013. Logistics manager responsible for operations of the conference including registration, AV equipment and support for speakers.
- Manchester Immunology Group Seminar Series, May 2017 Sep 2018. Co-lead organiser. Handling invitations, hospitality, communications, for renowned international speakers to visit University of Manchester.
- School talk, Oaklands Community College, Edenderry Co. Offaly. "The life of a scientist." 2021
- **Single Cell TCD Core facility**. I formed a working group in 2021 in Trinity college dublin to address the competitive disadvantage of not having a working single cell RNA-sequencing. My aim is to deliver a single cell RNA-seq service to TCD researchers on a cost per service basis that will act as a platform to develop a full core facility service.

Formal Training

Single Cell RNA-sequencing

Programming Courses

Earlham Institute, University of East

Anglia

• library preparation, sequencing, QC & analysis

Research IT, University of

Manchester

1 DAY COURSES 2017-2019

R for Data anlysis; High Performance Computing; unix envirnoment & version control

Home Office personal animal licence

University of Manchester

1 WEEK COURSE; ONGOING TRAINING

PIL A, B & C

1 WEEK COURSE

Fluorescent activated cell sorting University College Dublin

1 WEEK COURSE 2014

Theory and practical training using BD machines

Awards

2019	Best presentatio	n from selected	abstracts - Irish	Society of	Immunology
2010	Dest presentatio	I II OIII JCICCICC	abstracts mism	JUCICLY OF	IIIIIIIIIIIIIIIIIIIIIIIIIIIIIIIIIIIIII

- 2015 Visiting student training scheme Weizmann Institute of Science
- 2015 TBSI Post-Doc Research Day Runner up talk prize
- 2014 Milstein Travel Award International Cytokine society
- 2007 Valdicotrian Biochemistry with Immunology degree
- 2007 Best Undergraduate Research Poster Prize School of Biochemistry and Immunology

Teaching

2021 R programming, data visualisation and transcriptomic analysis (3 workshops)

MSc in Immunology

2016-2017 T cell differentiation, effector function and regulation (4 lectures)

BA(Mod)

2016-2017 Cancer immunology and immunotherapy (2 lectures) 2016-2017 EAE as a model for multiple sclerosis

BA(Mod)

2016-2017 T cell differentiation, effector function and regulation (2 lectures)

BA(Mod)

2014-2017 Introduction to parasite and type 2 Immune responses (3 lectures)

MSc in Immunology
MSc in Immunology

Other duties include Undergraduate practical supervision, tutorials, and organising visits of school students as various points between 2013-2016. Introduction to data scientists for immunologists course available here. Acting as an official 'external mentor' of a PhD student in Wellcome Trust in Immunomatrix in Complex Disease PhD program in Manchester.

Supervision

2 week student project Trinity College Dublin

Bachelor in Medicine 202

· Lab/statistical training. Continued Informal mentorship with one student.

3 month student project Trinity College Dublin

Ba(Mod)

• Co-primary supervisor – lab/statistical training, writing mentorship. Ongoing collaboration with a co-first author paper in preparation together.

Formal supervison

Research Assistant

2021

• Direct supervision and training. Daily interaction.

6 month student project

University of Manchester

Mres Infection Biology 2020-2021

· Co-primary supervisor - project design and mentorship & direct supervision/training, student now in UK graduate Industry role.

6 month student project University of Manchester

MRES INFECTION BIOLOGY 2018-2019

• Co-primary supervisor - project design and mentorship & direct supervision/training, student now a PhD Candidate in Leeds.

Informal mentorship Trinity College Dublin

PHD 2017-2021

Informal supervisor. Project design and management and career mentorship. Two papers published together, awarded best presentation at

ICS 2018. Now a Post-Doc in Glasgow.

3 month student project Trinity College Dublin

Msc Immunology 2016

• Co-primary supervisor - project design and mentorship & direct supervision/training. Sudent now a PhD candidate in TCD.

Informal mentorship Trinity College Dublin

PHD 2015-2017

· Informal supervisor. Project design and management.

3 month student project Trinity College Dublin

Msc Immunology 2015

• Co-primary supervisor - project design and mentorship & direct supervision/training. Project led to IRC-funded PhD that I co-wrote.

3 month student project Trinity College Dublin

MSC IMMUNOLOGY 20

 $\bullet \ \ \, \text{Co-primary supervisor - project design and mentorship \& direct supervision/training. Student now in Biotech Industry role.}$

Other Contributions

REVIEWING

2021 French National Research Agency (ANR) 2021 generic call

2021 BBSRC Discovery Fellows award

2018 Manuscript reviewing

2017-2020 Manuscript reviewing

Grant review Grant review Scientific Reports. Parasite Immunology

SOCIETY MEMBERSHIP

- British Society of immunology
- Irish society of Immunology
- International Cytokine & Interferon Society

Publications

- 1. Fiancette, R., Finlay, C. M., Willis, C., Bevington, S. L., Soley, J., Ng, S. T. H., Baker, S. M., Andrews, S., Hepworth, M. R., & Withers, D. R. (2021). Reciprocal transcription factor networks govern tissue-resident ILC3 subset function and identity. *Nature Immunology*. https://doi.org/10.1038/s41590-021-01024-x
- 2. Cunningham, K. T., Finlay, C. M., & Mills, K. H. G. (2021). Helminth Imprinting of Hematopoietic Stem Cells Sustains Anti-Inflammatory Trained Innate Immunity That Attenuates Autoimmune Disease. *The Journal of Immunology*, 206(7), 1618–1630. https://doi.org/10.4049/jimmunol.2001225
- 3. Finlay, C. M., Cunningham, K. T., Doyle, B., & Mills, K. H. G. (2020). IL-33–Stimulated Murine Mast Cells Polarize Alternatively Activated Macrophages, Which Suppress T Cells That Mediate Experimental Autoimmune Encephalomyelitis. *The Journal of Immunology*, 205(7), 1909–1919. https://doi.org/10.4049/jimmunol. 1901321
- 4. Finlay, C. M., & Allen, J. E. (2020). The immune response of inbred laboratory mice to Litomosoides sigmodontis: A route to discovery in myeloid cell biology. *Parasite Immunology*, 42(7), e12708. https://doi.org/10.1111/pim.12708
- 5. Czajkowska, B. I., Finlay, C. M., Jones, G., & Brown, T. A. (2019). Diversity of a cytokinin dehydrogenase gene in wild and cultivated barley. *PLOS ONE*, *14*(12), e0225899. https://doi.org/10.1371/journal.pone. 0225899
- 6. McEntee, C. P., Finlay, C. M., & Lavelle, E. C. (2019). Divergent Roles for the IL-1 Family in Gastrointestinal Homeostasis and Inflammation. *Frontiers in Immunology*, 10. https://doi.org/10.3389/fimmu.2019.01266
- 7. Campbell, S. M., Knipper, J. A., Ruckerl, D., Finlay, C. M., Logan, N., Minutti, C. M., Mack, M., Jenkins, S. J., Taylor, M. D., & Allen, J. E. (2018). Myeloid cell recruitment versus local proliferation differentiates susceptibility from resistance to filarial infection. *eLife*, 7, e30947. https://doi.org/10.7554/eLife.30947
- 8. Sutton, C. E., Finlay, C. M., Raverdeau, M., Early, J. O., DeCourcey, J., Zaslona, Z., O'Neill, L. A. J., Mills, K. H. G., Curtis, A. M., CE, S., CM, F., M, R., JO, E., J, D., Z, Z., LAJ, O., KHG, M., & AM, C. (2017). Loss of the molecular clock in myeloid cells exacerbates T cell-mediated CNS autoimmune disease. *Nature Communications*, 8(1), 1923. https://doi.org/10.1038/s41467-017-02111-0
- 9. Finlay, C. M., Stefanska, A. M., Coleman, M. M., Jahns, H., Cassidy, J. P., McLoughlin, R. M., & Mills, K. H. G. (2017). Secreted products of Fasciola hepatica inhibit the induction of T cell responses that mediate allergy. *Parasite Immunology*, 39(10), e12460. https://doi.org/10.1111/pim.12460
- 10. Walsh, K. P., Brady, M. T., Finlay, C. M., Boon, L., & Mills, K. H. G. (2009). Infection with a Helminth Parasite Attenuates Autoimmunity through TGF-M-Mediated Suppression of Th17 and Th1 Responses. *The Journal of Immunology*, 183(3), 1577–1586. https://doi.org/10.4049/jimmunol.0803803
- 11. Finlay, C. M., Walsh, K. P., & Mills, K. H. G. (2014). Induction of regulatory cells by helminth parasites: exploitation for the treatment of inflammatory diseases. *Immunological Reviews*, 259(1), 206–230. https://doi.org/10.1111/imr.12164

- 12. Coleman, M. M., Finlay, C. M., Moran, B., Keane, J., Dunne, P. J., & Mills, K. H. G. (2012). The immunoregulatory role of CD4 + FoxP3 + CD25 regulatory T cells in lungs of mice infected with Bordetella pertussis. FEMS Immunology & Medical Microbiology, 64(3), 413–424. https://doi.org/10.1111/j.1574-695X. 2011.00927.x
- Walsh, K. P., Brady, M. T., Finlay, C. M., Boon, L., & Mills, K. H. G. (2009). Infection with a Helminth Parasite Attenuates Autoimmunity through TGF-⊠-Mediated Suppression of Th17 and Th1 Responses. *The Journal of Immunology*, 183(3), 1577–1586. https://doi.org/10.4049/jimmunol.0803803

ARTICLES IN SUBMITTED OR IN PREPERATION

Finlay, CM, Parkinson, JP, Chan, BHK, Prise, I, Morrison, A, Ruckerl, D, Ajendra J, Chenery, A, Konkel, K, Boon, L, Baker, SM, Loke, P and Allen, JE. Genotype specific conversion into tissue macrophages requires IL-4R signalling in addition to cell intrinsic regulatory mechanisms during type 2 immunity.

Finlay, CM, . Parkinson, JP., Chan, BHK. and Allen, JE Pleural fluid of mice

Referees_

Prof Judi Allen

PROFESSOR OF IMMUNOBIOLOGY

• judi.allen@manchester.ac.uk

Dr Matthew Hepworth

SIR HENRY DALE FELLOW

· matthew.hepworth@manchester.ac.uk

Prof Kingston HG Mills

PROFESSOR OF EXPERIMENTAL IMMUNOLOGY

• kingston.mills@tcd.ie

Prof Cliona O'Farrelly

PROFESSOR OF COMPARATIVE IMMUNOLOGY

· ofarrecl@tcd.ie

CV made in Rmarkdown with Vitae R package

University of Manchester

Lydia Becker Institute of Immunology and Inflammation

University of Manchester

Lydia Becker Institute of Immunology and Inflammation

Trinity College Dublin

School of Biochemistry and Immunology

Trinity College Dublin

School of Biochemistry and Immunology